Guide to the Intercollegiate Center for Nursing Education Director (Hilda Boerhave Roberts) Papers 1924-2001
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Intercollegiate Center for Nursing Education Director (Hilda Boerhave Roberts) Papers
1924-2001
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Archives 317
Roberts, Hilda Boerhave
82.5 linear feet 163 boxes
This collection contains a variety of materials on nursing in Washington State and at WSU.
Hilda Boerhave was born in Lynden, WA on March 23, 1917 and graduated from Lynden High School. She married William S. Roberts in 1956. Hilda received her B.S. and a Master of Nursing from the University of Washington and attended Columbia University taking coursework towards a doctorate. She pursued her education and passion for nursing throughout her life with constant studies and efforts to develop the field of professional nursing in Washington. Hilda Roberts served in numerous national, state, and local nursing organizations and worked to expand the field of nursing during its formative years.
Hilda became an assistant professor and director of the School of Nursing at Washington State College (WSC) in 1948. She worked with both the Deaconess and St. Luke’s hospital divisions of the WSC nursing school in the 1940s and 1950s. At WSC and later WSU Hilda Roberts worked in Community College outreach, the College Transfer program, the WSU Extension Program, curricula design, and many other efforts that encouraged the development of the WSU Nursing School and nursing in Eastern Washington. Hilda Roberts also actively participated in numerous local, state, and national nursing organizations that were coming into their own during the postwar period and represent the core of the profession today. These organizations include the American Nurses Association, the National League for Nursing, the Washington State Nurses Association, the Whitman County Nurses Association and the Washington/Alaska Regional Medical Program.
Hilda Roberts worked with other nursing faculty to write the construction, capitation, and development grants that led to the creation of the ICNE in 1968. She served the college as the inaugural Director of the center from 1968-1972 and retired from WSU in 1982. Throughout her tenure she advised, taught, and mentored nursing students and worked tirelessly with other nursing faculty to cultivate the availability of nursing education in Eastern Washington. Mrs. Roberts passed away on September 29, 2011. The WSU College of Nursing carries a Hilda Roberts scholarship in her honor, begun the year of her retirement.
The Intercollegiate Center for Nursing Education (ICNE), created in 1968 and located in Spokane, Washington, was initially a consortium of Eastern Washington University, Whitworth College, Ft. George Wright College, and Washington State University (WSU), which coordinated the program. Students choose to enroll in one of the participating institution, at which they complete their lower division study and general education requirements. For their upper division work the students enter the Intercollegiate Center for Nursing Education, the first nursing consortium in the United States. Located in the medical and geographical center for Eastern Washington, Northern Idaho, Western Montana and border towns of Canada, the Center strives to meet the area's need for programs in nursing, thereby upgrading the practice of nursing in the local communities.
As the first nursing consortium in the U.S., the Center's history and development were accordingly well documented. An area which also consumed the Center's interest involved the method, and theory of nursing education. This issue was resolved in favor of the "holistic" approach to both nursing education and practice.
This collection contains a variety of materials on nursing in Washington State and at WSU. The collection comprises correspondence, photographs, newspapers and media articles, plans, schematics, meetings minutes, notes and a variety of other materials related to the overall life and work of Hilda Roberts, as well as a plethora of materials on nursing in Eastern Washington. The collections documents the twentieth century development of the profession of nursing as well as the struggles women faced earning respect and consideration as nurses in a field largely dominated by male physicians.
Though the Hilda Roberts papers required substantial reorganization and ordering, the original folders titles were maintained where possible. All notes on individual folders are reproductions of Hilda Roberts’ handwritten notes found on the original document folders. The years represented in each folder title represent the range of years present in the folder and not necessarily all the materials from that period.
The collection has five primary series, as well as one small series of oversized materials. The series are arranged by subject, with subseries and individual folders within each series arranged first alphabetically, and then chronologically.
Series 1: Professional Nursing Organizations, 1933-1996 – consists of materials from the variety of nursing organizations and institutions affiliated with faculty from the WSU Nursing School. These materials represent the activities of the WSU Nursing faculty and Hilda Roberts across a local, state, and national field of nursing.
Series 2: The Washington State College (WSC) Nursing School, 1936-1998 – This series contains considerable information, correspondence, and material from the WSU Department of Nursing Education and the St. Luke’s Hospital Clinical Division for the WSC School of Nursing. Contained herein is a wealth of information on nursing education in Eastern Washington before the development of the ICNE.
Subseries 2.1: WSC Nursing Faculty Organizations, 1941-1966 – Holdings include meeting minutes, correspondence, reports and materials from many of the nursing faculty organizations in the Washington State College School of Nursing.
Series 3: The Intercollegiate Center for Nursing Education (ICNE), 1935-2001 – This material embodies not just Hilda Roberts contribution to the Spokane nursing center, but all of the people and the entire process required to bring together the consortium nursing institution. This series details meetings, organizations, and efforts responsible for the development and growth of the ICNE. It contains correspondence, meeting minutes, and reports, as well as grants, construction plans, curriculum and philosophy development and a wealth of material relating to the faculty and the four universities involved in the ICNE.
Subseries 3.1: ICNE Faculty Organizations, 1965-1983 – Contained herein are faculty committee meeting minutes, reports, and correspondence from the various ICNE faculty organizations responsible for the administration of the center.M
Subseries 3.2: Student Life, 1942-2001 – This portion houses material involving WSC and WSU nursing students from the 1940s, including substantial holdings and photographs of nursing students, the Rho Nu student organization, and materials relating their experience at the WSU Nursing School.
Series 4: Hilda Roberts’ Personal Papers, 1924-1992, is a collection of Hilda Roberts’ research, activities, and biographical information. It contains some personal correspondence as well as detailed articles about her activities throughout her life.
Series 5 is a small set of oversized materials from the first four series.
Series 6: Nursing Courses, 1939-1997 - Curricula and course materials from the WSU nursing school representing most of the courses offered from the 1970s to the 1990s as well as numerous courses dating back to the 1950s.
This collection is open and available for research use.
This collection was compiled from six accessions, received at the Washington State University (WSU) Libraries’ Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections (MASC) between 1982 and 2010 from Hilda Roberts, the Intercollegiate Center for Nursing Education (ICNE), and the Spokane branch of the WSU Libraries. The six accessions were UA1982-05, UA1985-18, UA1988-13, UA2002-07, MS2002-26, MS2010-22. The collection was processed between June 2010 and April 2012 by WSU History PhD student Nathan Roberts and Courtney Buehn, for University Archivist Mark O’English. Processing and description of this collection was supported by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities to member institutions of the Washington Women’s History Consortium, a program managed by the Washington State Historical Society.
Additional materials from Hilda Roberts and various Nursing-related programs, including course materials, can be found in the following collections at MASC:
Cage 551: Hilda Roberts Papers, 1940-1972
Cage 650: Rho Nu Nursing Society Records, 1972-1993
Archives 54: Intercollegiate Center for Nursing Education Records, 1958-1975
Archives 233: Intercollegiate Center for Nursing Education Records, 1947-1993
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Intercollegiate Center for Nursing Education (Spokane, Wash.) -- Records and correspondence; Washington State University -- Faculty -- Archives
Nursing -- Study and teaching -- Washington (State); Nursing schools -- Washington (State) -- Administration -- Archival resources; Rho Nu Nursing Society -- Records and correspondence
Colleges and universities; Medicine and health
- Professional Nursing Organizations, Series 1
  - American Council on Pharmaceutical Education - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Nurses' Association Boerhave, Hilda, Second Chairman of E.A.C.T. - 1955 to 1956 (Folder 2)
  - American Nurses' Association Conferences and Conventions - 1946 to 1975 (Folder 3)
  - American Nurses' Association Correspondence, General - 1938 to 1981 (Folder 4)
  - American Nurses' Association Correspondence with Hilda Boerhave Roberts - 1948 to 1969 (Folder 5)
  - American Nurses' Association Data and Nursing Inventions - 1934 to 1981 (Folder 6)
  - American Nurses' Association Diamond Jubilee of Nursing - 1948 to 1975 (Folder 7)
  - American Nurses' Association Newspaper "American Nurses' Association in Action" - 1970 to 1971 (Folder 8)
  - American Nurses' Association News Release - 1950 to 1967 (Folder 9)
  - American Nurses' Association on Federal Aid to Nursing Education - 1951 to 1953 (Folder 10)
  - American Nurses' Association Pamphlets - 1940s to 1980s (Folder 11)
  - American Nurses' Association Papers and Publications - 1945 to 1973 (Folder 12)
  - American Nurses' Association Publication "Nursing Research" - 1968 (Folder 13)
  - American Nurses' Association Publication "Professional Nursing" - 1947 (Folder 14)
  - American Nurses' Association Publication "The American Journal of Nursing" - 1945 to 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Nurses' Association Publication "The American Nurse" - 1980 to 1982 (Folder 2)
  - American Red Cross Whitman County Chapter - 1949 to 1971 (Folder 3)
  - Army/Navy Nurse Corps Correspondence with ICNE - 1972 to 1980 (Folder 4)
  - Association of Collegiate Schools of Nursing - 1937 to 1948 (Folder 5)
  - Central Washington State College Report "Rural Health Care in Washington" - 1974 (Folder 6)
  - Council of Presidents Report "A Plan for Public Higher Education in Washington" - 1964 (Folder 7)
  - Council on Collegiate Education in Nursing in the State of Washington - 1971 to 1972 (Folder 8)
  - Deaconess Hospital (Spokane) Materials and Correspondence - 1965 to 1984 (Folder 9)
  - Idaho State Nurses Association, Correspondence and Materials - 1962 to 1980 (Folder 10)
  - Idaho State Nurses Association Nursing Refresher Courses at University of Idaho - 1961 to 1965 (Folder 11)
  - Inland Empire Nurses Association, District of WSNA, By-Laws and Organization Materials - 1951 to 1967 (Folder 12)
  - Inland Empire Nurses Association, Newsletters/Workshops - 1966 to 1974 (Folder 13)
  - International Council of Nurses, Materials and Reports - 1933 to 1947 (Folder 14)
  - Inter-University Committee on Center for Graduate Study in Richland -- Minutes and Information - 1966 to 1967 (Folder 15)
  - National League for Nursing Accreditation Information - 1950s to 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - National League for Nursing Achievement and Qualifying Exam Information - 1947 to 1971 (Folder 2)
  - National League for Nursing Biennial Convention - 1955 (Folder 3)
  - National League for Nursing Biennial Reports - 1963 to 1964 (Folder 4)
  - National League for Nursing Conference of the Council of Member Agencies, Minutes, and Materials - 1954 to 1966 (Folder 5)
  - National League for Nursing Conference of the Council of Member Agencies, Minutes, and Materials - 1967 to 1972 (Folder 6)
  - National League for Nursing Conference on "Developing Nursing Programs in Institutions of Higher Education" - 1968 (Folder 7)
  - National League for Nursing Consultants visit W.S.C. - 1954 to 1957 (Folder 8)
  - National League for Nursing Correspondence, General - 1955 to 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - National League for Nursing Correspondence with Hilda B. Roberts - 1947 to 1975 (Folder 2)
  - National League for Nursing Fact Sheets - 1963 to 1975 (Folder 3)
  - National League for Nursing Guide for Tuberculosis and Psychiatric Nursing - 1955 (Folder 4)
  - National League for Nursing Northwest Regional Conference - 1953 (Folder 5)
  - National League for Nursing Notes and Materials Collected by Hilda B. Roberts - 1956 to 1965 (Folder 6)
  - National League for Nursing Nursing Evaluation Guidelines and Workshops - 1949 to 1972 (Folder 7)
  - National League for Nursing Pamphlets - 1933 to 1980 (Folder 8)
  - National League for Nursing Publication "A Validation Study of the National League for Nursing Pre-Nursing and Guidance Examination" - 1970 (Folder 9)
  - National League for Nursing Publication "Convention Outlook" - May, 1965 (Folder 10)
  - National League for Nursing Publication " Memo to Members" and Other Memos - 1946 to 1982 (Folder 11)
  - National League for Nursing Publication "National League for Nursing News" - 1964 to 1980 (Folder 12)
  - National League for Nursing Publication "Nursing Education Facilities" - 1964 (Folder 13)
  - National League for Nursing Publication "Nursing Outlook" - 1954 to 1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - National League for Nursing Publication "The Head Nurse at Work" - 1953 (Folder 2)
  - National League for Nursing Publications and Studies on Nursing Education - 1966 to 1975 (Folder 3)
  - National League for Nursing Publications on Accreditation and Evaluation - 1944 to 1975 (Folder 4)
  - National League for Nursing Publications on Structural Revisions of Nursing Organizations - 1946 to 1966 (Folder 5)
  - National League for Nursing Questionnaires and Reports - 1952 to 1972 (Folder 6)
  - National League for Nursing Report from St. Luke's School of Nursing - 1951 to 1955 (Folder 7)
  - National League for Nursing Report "ICNE Self-Evaluation Accreditation Report" - 1974 (Folder 8)
  - National League for Nursing Reports on Council of Baccalaureate and Higher Degree Programs - 1956 to 1971 (Folder 9)
  - National League for Nursing Reports on Nursing Education - 1953 to 1972 (Folder 10)
  - National League for Nursing Sample Self-Evaluating Report, University of Illinois - 1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - National League for Nursing Self-Evaluation Guide for Nursing - 1954 to 1969 (Folder 2)
  - National League for Nursing Western Regional Assembly Documents - 1968 to 1976 (Folder 3)
  - National League for Nursing Education Correspondence, General - 1946 to 1950 (Folder 4)
  - National League for Nursing Education Correspondence with Hilda Roberts - 1948 to 1951 (Folder 5)
  - National League for Nursing Education Nursing Organization Curriculum Conferences - 1949 to 1951 (Folder 6)
  - National League for Nursing Education Publication: "Manual of the Essentials of Good Hospital Nursing Service" - 1936 to 1942 (Folder 7)
  - National League for Nursing Education Reports and Conventions - 1941 to 1950 (Folder 8)
  - National Nursing Accrediting Service, Accreditation Report from Sacred Heart School of Nursing - 1949 to 1953 (Folder 9)
  - National Nursing Accrediting Service Temporary Accreditation Report - 1951 to 1954 (Folder 10)
  - National Nursing Council "A Thousand Think Together: A Report of Three Regional Conferences" - 1947 (Folder 11)
  - North Idaho Consortium for Health Education, Seminar Materials - 1981 to 1985 (Folder 12)
  - Northeast Washington League For Nursing - 1964 (Folder 13)
  - Northwest Association of Secondary and Higher Schools - 1953 to 1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Oregon League For Nursing Publication "The Oregon Reporter" No. 3 - 1969 (Folder 2)
  - Seattle Hospital Council Workshop on Hospital Nursing Functions - 1957 to 1958 (Folder 3)
  - Spokane Community College Associate Degree Nursing Advisory Committee Materials and Correspondence - 1969 to 1971 (Folder 4)
  - Spokane Community College Associate Degree in Nursing Proposals - 1969 to 1976 (Folder 5)
  - Spokane county Health Department Correspondence with Nursing Faculty - 1943 to 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Spokane County Health Department Materials and Reports on Public Health Nursing - 1950s (Folder 7)
  - Spokane League for Nursing and Inland Empire Nurses Association Joint Committee on Nursing Education--Correspondence/Materials/Surveys - 1964 to 1968 (Folder 8)
  - Spokane League for Nursing and Inland Empire Nurses Association Joint Committee on Nursing Education, Minutes - 1964 to 1965 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Spokane League for Nursing Correspondence and Organization Materials - 1960s (Folder 2)
  - Spokane League for Nursing Steering Committee on Nursing Education--Correspondence/Materials - 1965 to 1967 (Folder 3)
  - Spokane League for Nursing Steering Committee on Nursing Education--Minutes/Reports - 1965 to 1967 (Folder 4)
  - Spokane League for Nursing Subcommittee of the Steering Committee on Nursing Education, Minutes and Reports - 1965 to 1966 (Folder 5)
  - Spokane League for Nursing Subcommittee of the Steering Committee on Nursing Education, "Report on Proposed Plan for an Inter-institutional Approach…" - April, 1966 (Folder 6)
  - Spokane Visiting Nurses Association Correspondence with Hilda B. Roberts - 1943 to 1967 (Folder 7)
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Correspondence and Materials - 1964 to 1972 (Folder 8)
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare--Course Materials "Washington State Health Mobilization Training Course" - 1962 (Folder 9)
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare--Program "Nursing Student Loan Program" - 1964 to 1965 (Folder 10)
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Publication "Health Manpower Education News" - 1971 to 1976 (Folder 11)
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Publication "Health Mobilization Course Manual" - 1960s (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - United States Federal Security Agency Materials on Cadet and Army Nurse Corps - 1940 to 1971 (Folder 2)
  - United States Federal Security Agency Newsletter "Cadet Nurse Corps" - 1946 to 1947 (Folder 3)
  - United States Federal Security Agency Publication "A Report of Washington Nursing Study" - 1950 (Folder 4)
  - United States Federal Security Agency, United States Public Health Service Division of Nurse Education Correspondence - 1944 to 1951 (Folder 5)
  - United States Navy Publication: "Angel of the Orient" - 1966 (Folder 6)
  - United States Office of Naval Officer Procurement, Correspondence and Materials - 1940s to 1950s (Folder 7)
  - United States Public Health Service: One Minute Film "Are you an Inactive Nurse" - 1940s (Folder 8)
  - University of Washington Council on Collegiate Nursing in Washington - 1971 to 1972 (Folder 9)
  - University of Washington Report "Collegiate Education in Nursing in the State of Washington" - 1971 (Folder 10)
  - Washington/Alaska Regional Medical Program Conferences, Activities, and Questionnaires - 1967 to 1970 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Washington/Alaska Regional Medical Program Correspondence - 1968 to 1974 (Folder 2)
  - Washington/Alaska Regional Medical Program Minutes and Publications - 1968 to 1975 (Folder 3)
  - Washington/Alaska Regional Medical Program Report "Inactive Nurses in Washington State" - 1968 (Folder 4)
  - Washington/Alaska Regional Medical Program Report "Sub-Regional Coronary Care Educational Program" - 1968 (Folder 5)
  - Washington State Accreditation Schools of Professional Nursing Conference of Representatives - 1956 (Folder 6)
  - Washington State Board of Nursing, Accreditation Materials - 1961 to 1979 (Folder 7)
  - Washington State Board of Nursing, Accreditation Reports and Instructions - 1954 to 1978 (Folder 8)
  - Washington State Board of Nursing, Correspondence - 1964 to 1973 (Folder 9)
  - Washington State Board of Nursing "Annual Report" - 1960 to 1970 (Folder 10)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration, Accreditation Materials and Reports - 1950 to 1960 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration Committee Meeting Minutes and Materials - 1942 to 1965 (Folder 2)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration Correspondence with Hilda B. Roberts, Board Member - 1947 to 1965 (Folder 3)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration Correspondence with Nursing Faculty - 1941 to 1965 (Folder 4)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration, Materials and Correspondence on WSC School of Nursing Closure - 1949 to 1957 (Folder 5)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration Report, "Annual Report of Washington State College St. Luke's School of Nursing" - 1951 to 1959 (Folder 6)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration, Report on Flexible Educational Standards - 1957 to 1959 (Folder 7)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration Reports on Nursing in Washington State - 1939 to 1958 (Folder 8)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration Reports, "Quarterly Report" of St. Luke's School of Nursing - 1951 to 1954 (Folder 9)
  - Washington State Board of Professional Nurse Registration, Seattle Pacific College Application to Establish a Nursing School - 1965 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Washington State Council on Higher Education "Proposal for a Program of Assistance to Private College and University Nursing Education" - 1971 to 1973 (Folder 2)
  - Washington State Department of Health, Division of Nursing Correspondence and Materials - 1967 to 1970 (Folder 3)
  - Washington State Department of Health, Maternal and Child Health Conference--Materials and Hilda B. Roberts Notes - 1957 (Folder 4)
  - Washington State Department of Public Health Subcommittee on Nursing Reports and Materials - 1947 to 1949 (Folder 5)
  - Washington State Dietetic Association Newsletters - 1955 (Folder 6)
  - Washington State Heart Association Cardiac Nursing Conferences, Correspondence and Initiatives - 1953 to 1958 (Folder 7)
  - Washington State Heart Association Cardiac Nursing Conferences Committee Minutes and Conference Evaluations - 1955 (Folder 8)
  - Washington State Heart Association Cardiac Nursing Conference News Releases and Newspaper Articles - 1952 to 1958 (Folder 9)
  - Washington State Heart Association Cardiac Nursing Conference Photo Negatives - 1958 (Folder 10)
  - Washington State Heart Association Cardiac Nursing Conferences, Research and Conference Materials - 1951 to 1958 (Folder 11)
  - Washington State Hospital Association "Conference on the Nurse Shortage" - 1963 (Folder 12)